Guide to the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- AMERICAN TRIP, APRIL 1831--APRIL 1832; B.
  - Miscellaneous materials about American Trip and American contacts found by G. W. Pierson in U.S., 5
    - a. Photostats of Francis Lieber correspondence (Box 15)
      -22 July 1846, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber, 2 sheets (From Hunt: Robson: Not to be used without permission of that library)
      -22 July 1846, Mme de Tocqueville to Francis Lieber, 2 sheets (From Hunt: Robson: Not to be used without permission of that library)
      -28 Sept. 1846, copy of Francis Lieber to Tocqueville, 2 sheets (From Hunt: Robson: Not to be used without permission of that library)
      -7 mars, 1849, Paris, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber, 2 sheets (From Hunt: Robson: Not to be used without permission of that library)
      -4 aout 1852, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber, 4 sheets (From Hunt: Robson: Not to be used without permission of that library)
      -1 7bre 1856, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Francis Lieber, 2 sheets (From Hunt: Robson: Not to be used without permission of that library)
      -18 Feb. 1861, Beaumont-la-Chartre, Beaumont to Francis Lieber, 2 sheets (From Hunt: Robson: Not to be used without permission of that library)
    - B.V.b. Great Lakes: Photostats of newspaper account of trip. (GWP) (Box 15)
    - c. Photostats from Neilson (Mondelet) papers. (GWP) (Box 15)
    - d. See also GWP notes, E.IV.a; E.IV.b (Box 15)
- THE WRITING OF THEIR BOOKS, ETC., 1832-1840; C.
  - Letters, 1
    - a. Tocqueville-Beaumont Correspondence, 1830-1840.
      - 1. Beaumont to Tocqueville: Manuscript "Paquet 11" in 3 cahiers (for third cahier, see D.I.b.). Unfortunately not in strict chronological order. Jardin says some of the originals have been lost (1963). (Box 16)
        -6 8bre (1832?), St. Sauveur, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -7 aout 1833, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -24 aout, 1833, Beaumont-la-Chartre, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -17 mai (1833, 1834?), Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -2 juillet, 1837, Dublin, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -27 juillet, 1837, Dublin, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -3 7bre 1837, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -7 7bre 1837 [?], Le Mans, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -26 7bre 1837, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -5 8bre (1837), Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -7 8bre (1837), Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -15 octobre 1837, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -23 8bre 1837, [Paris?], Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -18 Xbre 1837 [?], Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -"vendredi matin", Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -n.d., Londres, ou plutot Kensington Sq. no. 6, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -15 janvier, 1838, La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -28 janvier, (1838?), La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -23 mars [1838], La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -10 juin 1838, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -1er juillet, 1838, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -25 8bre 1838, La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -4 9bre [1838], St. Calais, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -8 9bre [1838], Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -29 9bre [1838], La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -"vendredi matin", La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -"mercredi matin", La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -22 janvier 1839, La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -9 fevrier samedi, 1839?, 1849?, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -16 fevrier 1839, St. Calais, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -8 mars 1839, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -31 juillet 1839, Beaumont-la-Chartre, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -16 aout 1839, Beaumont-la-Chartre, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -2 8bre 18, Beaumont-la-Chartre, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -14 8bre 1839, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -26 8bre 1839, La Grange par Rosay, Bt, to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -10 novembre 1839, La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -15 juillet 1840, Mamers, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -20 juillet 1840, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -24 juillet 1840, Paris, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -7 aout 1840, La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
        -25 aout 1840, La Grange, Beaumont to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS, T:I.C.3.a.)
      - 2. Tocqueville to Beaumont Letters: (Chiefly originals from Mme de Larminat.) (Box 16)
        -8 mai, 1830, Versailles, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -16 mai, 1830, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -11-14 mars, 1831, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original, also GWP copy)
        -4 avril 1832, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original) (For copy, see B.I.a.2. above.)
        -10 avril 1832, St. Germain, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -[Fin juillet 1833] lundi soir, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Ext. by White from copy made by Mme de Tocqueville:;see White Cat. 2W: IV, p.7, Ext. 5)
        -13 aout, 1833, London, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -1 nov. 1833, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -5 juillet, 1834, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -14 juillet, 1834, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -12 aout 1834, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -24 oct. 1834, Versailles, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -12 janvier 1835, Compiegne, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -1 avril 1835, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -26 aout, 1835, Nacqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -31 oct.? 1835, Compiegne, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -15 nov. 1835, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -7 juin (inc.) 1836, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -14 juin, 1836, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -6 juillet 1836, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -30 juillet 1836, Berne, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -5 sept. 1836, Interlachen, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -22 sept. 1836, Nacqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -4 nov. 1836, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -22 nov. 1836, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -14 mai 1837, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -26 mai 1837, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -9 juillet 1837, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original- with extract by GWP from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
        -18 juillet, 1837, Cherbourg, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -12 nov. 1837, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -11 dec. 1837, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -24 dec. 1837, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -18 jan. 1838, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -21 mars 1838, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -22 avril 1838, Baugy, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -15 juin 1838, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -8 juillet 1838, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -25 juillet 1838, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -8 aout, 1838, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -30 sept. 1838, Nacqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -19 oct. 1838, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -9 nov. 1838, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -9 jan. 18399 Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -30 janv. 1839, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -31 janv., 1839, Paris, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -3 fevr. 1839, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -15 fevr. 1839, Valognes, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -28 fevr. 1839, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -7 mars 1839, Valognes, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -11 mars 1839, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -4 aout 1839, Caen, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -23 oct. 1839, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -4 nov. 1839, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -5 dec. 1839, Tocqueville, Tocqueville to Beaumont (Original)
        -ce jeudi matin (no year), note from Alexis de Tocqueville to Gustave saying that Alexis' father wanted to dine with Gustave, and setting an hour. On the back of the invitation are notes by Gustave on the theory and psychology of philanthropists (possibly from some conversation with Tocqueville?) (Larminat to GWP)
        -three empty envelopes of 1832, 1833 and 1837 from Tocqueville to Beaumont: the first has on its verso a note by Tocqueville on the inhabitants of Provence as being the true Italians of France (Larminat to GWP)
    - C.I.b. Tocqueville Correspondence with his wife, Mary Mottley: 183?-1859. (Box 16)
      Tocqueville's letters to his wife have presented a problem. In 1930 [?] GWP saw some extracts or fragmentary copies from a few early letters, purportedly in MM's hand (see beginning and end of list below), and was led to believe that all the originals had been destroyed. Many years later GWP and the Yale Library acquired from Mme de Larminat the originals of 29 other letters, often undated, and numbered (out of their probable order) in red ink. These have now been put into the sequence suggested by Hugh Brogan. See Brogan's informative and suggestive discussion of them in the C.I.b. folder. (GWP 1964)
      -18 mai 1832, "A! le triste temps...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (GWP extract from copy in Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
      -3 juin 1832, "... Je suis triste et inquiet, Marie." Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (GWP extract from copy in Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
      -20 juillet 1833, Naqueville, Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (GWP extract from copy at Tocqueville?)
      -2 aout 1834, Cherbourg, Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (GWP note from copy at Tocqueville?)
      -23 aout 1834, Beaumont-la-Chartre, Tocqueville to Mary Mottley "Je ne serais jamais heureux..." (GWP extract from copy at Tocqueville?)
      -5 mai 1835, London, Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (White extract from ?)
      -19 xbre 1837, Paris, "J'ai ete tout a fait peine hier..." (red ink #"22") (Original from Larminat)
      -ce dimanche matin [21 Oct. 1837, Valognes?] "ma petite amie cherie, je suis tout honteux...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"23") (Original from Larminat)
      -dimanche soir, [20 June?] 1837, "J'ai recu hier ton paquet", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"27") (Original from Larminat)
      -26 Dec. 1837 [Paris], "j'ai recu hier au soir ta lettre du dimanche", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"16") (Original from Larminat)
      -ce mardi matin, [August?] 1843, St. Lo, "Ta premiere lettre que j'attendais...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"25") (Original from Larminat)
      -mercredi matin [Aug.- Sept. 1843?, St. Lo] "Je me leve a cinq heures du matin...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"24") (Original from Larminat)
      -vendredi [1 August?] 1844, "A peine etais-tu hier dans la voiture...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"26") (Original from Larminat)
      -ce jeudi matin, [August 7] 1844 [Paris?], "Je t'aime de tout mon coeur ...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"30") (Original from Larminat)
      -vendredi soir, 1845, St. Lo, "Quoique je t'aie ecrit hier...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"28") (Original from Larminat)
      -15 aout 1846, Cherbourg samedi, "je ne veux pas aller plus loin...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"21") (Original from Larminat)
      -[Paris?] 7 [August?] 1846, "Quoique je t'aie ecrit hier... j'aime a le faire de nouveau ", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"29") (Original from Larminat)
      -samedi matin, [August] 1846 [Paris?] "je n'ai point parle hier...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"20") (Original from Larminat)
      -20 aout 1848, St. Lo, ce vendredi, "Je suis arrive hier 8 au soir ici", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"14") (Original from Larminat)
      -[St. Lo?] ce jeudi soir, 1848 [or 1849?], "je viens, amie cherie, de trouver", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"14") (Original from Larminat)
      -ce jeudi soir [St. Lo?] 1851, "chere amie, je t'ecris a la hate..." Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"l8") (Original from Larminat)
      - [1851?] "Trois lettres de toi en trois jours... " Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"l7") (Original from Larminat)
      -[1851?] NacquevilIe, ce dimanche matin, "J'esperais avoir une lettre de toi hier...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"10") (Original from Larminat)
      -[1851?], Tocqueville, ce jeudi matin, "C'est enfin de Tocqueville que je t'ecris...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"l5") (Original from Larminat)
      -dimanche matin 18 [185--?], "Je travaille beaucoup, mon amie cherie...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"11") (Original from Larminat)
      -mardi matin [London, 16 June 1857?], "Je viens de faire une petite escapade", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"7") (Original from Larminat)
      -samedi matin, London, [20 June?] 1857, "si ma lettre n'etait si solidement...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"5") (Original from Larminat)
      -mercredi matin, 1 juillet [1857?], "Lanjuinais enfin sort de chez moi...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"6") (Original from Larminat)
      -vendredi matin [London, July 1857?], "je continue le cours de ma vie", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"9") (Original from Larminat)
      -vendredi 10 juillet 1857, "j'ai une grande satisfaction..." Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"8") (Original from Larminat)
      -vendredi soir [London, July 1857?], "Je viens de recevoir enfin...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"5") (Original from Larminat)
      [Not Satisfactorily Dated]
      -samedi matin 10, "pour commencer...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"12") (Original from Larminat)
      -ce dimanche matin [1851?], "je recois ta lettre d'hier...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"14") (Original from Larminat)
      -mercredi matin 21, "J'ai [illegible] et d'eu..." Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"13") (Original from Larminat)
      -ce vendredi 2h. [Normandy?], "Je t'ecris en arrivant...", Tocqueville to Mary Mottley (red ink #"3") (Original from Larminat)
      -Three undated documents, in letter-note form, quoting from Tocqueville letters. Copyist was probably his wife, Mary Mottley.
      1. "Pensees detachees d'Alexis. Ceci n'est point une point une exageration... a le risquer. " (Copy from Larminat)
      "Je n'ai jamais pu partager... atteintes du tems" (A love letter, probably rather early, addressed to "vous". Admits he thought he had been in love 12 years earlier.)
      2. 2 Pages: "Dans la citation que tu me fais de ses lettres... males ou femelles, je n'en exempte aucun." (A letter expressing his scorn for the bourgeois and the priests who fall over themselves for the new dictator.) (Copy from Larminat)
      3. 2 1/2 pages, 2 quotations. "Vous dites peut-etre avec raison que j'attache trop d'importance, quant a la foi, aux accidents de la conduite du clerge... derriere eux."
      "le seizieme siecle... harmonie d'ensemble."
      -empty sleeves, the first in Redier's hand, the second in Clementine's hand, purporting to contain extracts of the letters of Tocqueville to Clementine (Larminat to GWP)
      -deaths of Alexis and Mary Mottley
      -Cannes, 4 mars (postmarked 5 mars 1859), letter of Mary Mottley to Clementine de Beaumont asking forgiveness for insisting that Gustave come to stay with them at Cannes (Larminat to GWP)
      -undated letter and undated note (both evidently from the end of 1864) from Mary de Tocqueville to Gustave de Beaumont, asking him to come bury her and take care of her affairs as she will have died (Larminat to GWP)
      -23 Xbre 1864, letter from H. Thion from Valognes, announcing the death of Mary de Tocqueville to Clementine de Beaumont, and enclosing a lock of hair (on verso, "recit de la mort de Mme de Tocqueville, le 22 dec. 1864" in Clementine's hand) (Larminat to GWP)
      -two cards: "Priez pour l'ame de Marie Mottley" (Larminat to GWP)
    - C.I.c. Tocqueville and Beaumont French Correspondence, 1832-1840 (Box 16)
      -juin 1834, Tocqueville to ? (about R-C-) (White extract from ?)
      -31 juillet 1834, Tocqueville to Charles Stoffels (GWP copy from Stoffels d'Hautefort copy)
      -11 jan. 1835, Paris, Chateaubriand to Tocqueville (White Extract from Redier MSS:; see White Cat. 2W: Package 6, Dossier 7)
      -14 mars 1835, Paris, Dehault to Tocqueville (ALS from Larminat)
      -"je suis aussi profondement convaincu... " (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS: fragment of letter to Louis de Kergorlay or Eugene Stoffels published by Beaumont)
      -18 avril 1836, Paris, M. Berenger to Tocqueville and Beaumont (Original from Larminat)
      -1 juin 1836, Baugy, Tocqueville to Henry Reeve (White extract from Redier MSS [?])
      -16 juillet 1836, Metz, Eugene Stoffels to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS)
      -1836, Tocqueville to Merimee [?] (White extract ? from Redier MSS:; see White Cat. 3W: "3,3")
      -1836, Tocqueville to M. de Metz? (White extract ? from Redier MSS:; see White Cat. 3W: "3,3")
      -1836, Tocqueville to [Felix Le Peletier d'Aunay?] (White extract from Redier MSS [?])
      -20 oct. 1836, Casparin to De Metz about Tocqueville and Beaumont (Original from Larminat)
      -7 jan. 1837, Charles Remusat to Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat)
      -27 nov. 1837, Paris, M. to Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat)
      -8 dec. 1837, Paris, Ministry of Interior to Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat)
      -1837, Tocqueville to Royer-Collard (White extract from Redier MSS [?])
      -23 janv. 1838, Ministry of Interior to Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat)
      -24 aout 1838, Lyon, Bonnardel to Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat)
      -13 mars 1839, Valognes, Tocqueville to Uncle Rosambo (White extract from Redier MSS [?])
      -Toulon, 21 mai 1832, Beaumont copy of Tocqueville's letter of resignation to the Procureur General (Larminat to GWP)
      For rest of Tocqueville French Correspondence of 1832-1840, see Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS.
      See also C.XI. and GWP notes in E.IV.b. Hugh Brogan apparently found in the "Rubish" of Tocqueville's chapter on Honor (C.V.g.) two letters of Herve de Tocqueville, a letter of Tocqueville to Louis de Kergorlay on ambition, with a reply, and records of conversations with Robinson, and with his family, 1837.
    - C.I.d. Tocqueville and Beaumont Relations with Americans, 1832-1840: Letters, diaries, notes, etc. (Box 16)
      -21 sept. 1831, Boston, Francis Lieber to Beaumont and Tocqueville (Original from Larminat: see Lieber folder)
      -14 fevr. 1832, Boston, Francis Lieber to Tocqueville and Beaumont (Original from Larminat: see Lieber folder)
      -5 march, 1832, Francis Lieber to Tocqueville and Beaumont [?] (Original from Larminat: see Lieber folder)
      -25 June 1832, Phila., Robert Walsh to Tocqueville (Original from Larminat: GWP note from Beaumont-la-Chartre)
      -8 Oct. 1832, Phila., D'Annery to Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat: GWP note from Beaumont-la-Chartre)
      -15 Oct. 1832, Wash., Serurier a Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat: GWP note from Beaumont-la-Chartre)
      -18 Oct. 1832, Paris, Tocqueville to Jared Sparks (GWP copy from H: Sparks)
      -Beaumont article on Lieber Encycl. (Brouillon copy from Larminat: GWP note from Beaumont-la-Chartre See Lieber folder)
      -16 9bre, 1832, Paris, Beaumont to Francis Lieber (Photostat from Hunt: See B.V.a.)
      -19 Nov. 1832, N.Y., Francis Lieber to Tocqueville and Beaumont (Original from Larminat: GWP note from Beaumont-la-Chartre)
      -7 Jan. 1833, N.Y., Francis Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat: GWP note from Beaumont-la-Chartre)
      -23 Jan. (1833), N.Y., Francis Gustave de Beaumont (Original from Larminat: GWP note from Beaumont-la-Chartre)
      -12? June, (1833), Francis Lieber note (Memo by Lieber sent via John Pickering of Boston) (Robson-Hunt: See B.V.a.)
      -30 Aug. 1833, Boston, Jared Sparks to Tocqueville (Bonnel copy from Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS; GWP copy from H: Sparks)
      -24 Sept. 1833, Philadelphia, H.D. Gilpin to Tocqueville (Larminat)
      -28 Nov. 1833, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -29 Nov. 1833, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -2 Dec. 1833, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -14 Dec. 1833, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -4 Jan. 1834, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -6 Jan. 1834, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -7 Jan. 1834, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -20 Jan. 1834, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -24 Jan. 1834, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)
      -8 Feb. 1834, (Paris), Theodore Sedgwick diary note (GWP copy from MHS: Norton)